[SPEAKER_00]: So, I thought we could discuss authenticity as the... or the lack of authenticity is the main obstacle to understanding the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, first of all, like, instead of describing authenticity in positive terms,
[SPEAKER_02]: Can we come up with some way to describe how lack of authenticity would be most concretely manifested in people?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like?
[SPEAKER_02]: There's lying to others, of course, which is, like, even further into the rabbit hole of authenticity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Inauthenticity, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you lie to others, it will be impossible to stop lying to yourself, which fundamentally is what lack of authenticity is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Inauthenticity.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lying to yourself, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Things are assured in a way, but you insist in regarding them in another way, because it's more comfortable.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, yeah, that would be one way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is there something that... Let's say somebody who hasn't found a way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there a way to know that they are not being authentic, just based on how they go through life, how they feel?
[SPEAKER_04]: Somebody can ask if they have an attitude of personal responsibility for everything they do, say, think and feel.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's an attitude that one can adopt and can develop.
[SPEAKER_04]: And to the extent that one does not have that sense of full, complete responsibility, I would say someone is inauthentic.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but how would it more accurately, like, feel not to have that attitude versus having that attitude?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, somebody, for example, might feel like a victim of circumstances, like the origin of my pain is coming from outside, external, and so the problem needs to be resolved out there, in an assumed external world, rather than on the level of one's own views and actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, so that would be, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: I was referring more to like...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as a result of this, that you're talking about now, a person would feel a sense of safety, but a sense of false safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because not acknowledging things, or not recognizing the truth of things, in the most general sense, not recognizing
[SPEAKER_02]: Or acknowledge it the way things are.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in some mystical sense, but generally the state of affairs, let's say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Results in a form of ignorance is bliss, as they say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Uh-huh, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, practically speaking, that's why the the suttas are saying that recognizing dukkha can only result in two things, either noble search or madness, bewilderment, because
[SPEAKER_02]: Recognizing dukkha is basically recognizing or acknowledging the state of affairs, not in an external sense, but internally, like your liability to lose things that are dear to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your liability to doubt, not knowing what the way out of suffering is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Liability to uncertainty, to sickness, aging, and death.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, these are things that, by not acknowledging them, you would feel a sense of relief, but it's an unfounded relief.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, what I'm getting at is that if a person doesn't feel a sense of... not like acute, kind of like, you know,
[SPEAKER_02]: falling apart, sort of, constant anxiety, but just a subtle sense of unease, like something is not right.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, it has to be either because they are an arahant or they are covering something up, because you are liable to sickness, aging and death.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unless you're narahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, that has to be recognized.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you keep that recognition, if you're not covering it up, which is fundamentally like what authenticity is, not covering those fundamental liabilities up, then, well, it's gonna have to feel... there's gonna have to be some degree of dissonance there, some degree of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, discomforts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's one of the ways to measure lack of authenticity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you have the sense that everything will be all right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things will just turn out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have a reason to believe.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have a justification why you believe that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just like, I just live life as if things are going to be all right in the end.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's covering up a fundamental
[SPEAKER_00]: Perhaps we can find more ways in which
[SPEAKER_04]: Inauthenticity manifests.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, for example, if if one finds justification for certain action or views because the majority thinks like that, right, or because you belong to a certain group, or a society holds certain values like this, and then just uncritically taking that over can be a way of of having that false sense of safety and security by just doing what everybody else is doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, authenticity implies stepping away from that, which means that you're going to find yourself more on your own and that is experientially unpleasant, because one's ignorance or doubt about what is right, what is wrong, what are going to be the consequences of my actions and so on, that's going to be highlighted if you are not just
[SPEAKER_04]: Casually moving along with what an anonymous they or a crowd or a herd happens to be doing.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's another way, which doesn't mean that one cannot associate with other people, externally, objectively, but we're talking about an inner attitude of not just doing something because a certain group or a certain tradition
[SPEAKER_04]: tells you that that's good to do.
[SPEAKER_04]: What needs to be more critical than that?
[SPEAKER_02]: And recognizing, even if... even if you follow... it's not like I will not do anything, because in the end, you would be trusting yourself, still, when you go... when you... if you just assume that by not following anyone, you're already being authentic, that that wouldn't be the case, because
[SPEAKER_02]: You might still be covering up the fact that you yourself are still liable to doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you're not sure what's what's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not enough to just dismiss all authority authorities, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a fundamental recognition.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether I agree with others or not, I don't know what is correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I will be agreeing with something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's inevitable.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then,
[SPEAKER_00]: The underlying problem can only be fixed by recognizing that liability to doubt, not by finding ways to stop recognizing it so that it stops hurting.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it's... the dhamma goes against the grain, basically, because in order to recognize... in order to work towards fixing a problem, you have to keep it in sight.
[SPEAKER_02]: And keeping it in sight
[SPEAKER_02]: Metaphorically speaking, in this case, it's not going to be pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you have a any kind of illness...
[SPEAKER_00]: Going through a life-threatening illness, in this case, which is ignorance, like not understanding the Four Noble Truths, should be considered like the worst of all illnesses, because it is the thing that subjects you to the to the worst type of pain of, you know, rebirth and sickness, aging and death, even in this very life.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any kind of sickness that you could get,
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, bodily sickness is kind of secondary to the fundamental sickness of not knowing the way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only way that any worldly thing would be able to affect you.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, keeping that in sight, it's like, you can either forget that you have terminal cancer and... and, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: Kind of... not even like you you were told and you decided to forget about it, but like you have a sense that it could be, but you kind of... you don't go to the doctor to ask.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just decide to live
[SPEAKER_00]: The rest of your time, whatever that is, in the comfort of just not having to think about that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what more like what inauthenticity is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like you knew it and then you decided to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like you have a vague sense that there's something there, but you're refusing to acknowledge it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Like in a room, you might have, you know, a dark corner of the room.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not necessarily in sight, but it's there, and like, it's the dirt is building up in that corner.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and you postpone actually going there and cleaning it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what, that's more what it's like.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all this external
[SPEAKER_00]: Conformity to tradition and all that sort of stuff, those are just like the different mechanisms that you could use to cover up that liability to uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if the group says something, and you go along with it, well, that provides that kind of... that distraction from having to question, like, well, whether or not they are right,
[SPEAKER_02]: Is the problem that I am addressing through this, whatever it might be, even the right problem to focus on in the first place?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you recognize there's so much stuff to doubt, to question, that in the end, any sort of... any sort of, like, fixed first principle that you start from could be could be put into question.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: That can't be something that you find safety in, if you are recognizing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be at least somewhat unsettling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, a desire for, let's say, distraction, or doing things in order to feel comfortable,
[SPEAKER_04]: By definition, it means that there are things that one wants to distract oneself from, or that there is an underlying discomfort that one doesn't want to face.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, rather than spending time to organize one's pleasures and comforts, like on the inner, let's say, emotional or psychological level, not like having a roof over your head and some clothes to wear, that's quite necessary, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: So, we're talking on another level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then,
[SPEAKER_04]: Someone who is authentic would recognize that and turn around.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, what is it that I'm right now not wanting to see, through my desire to be distracted or to dissolve in a group and things like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that has got to become the habit.
[SPEAKER_04]: If one wants to move towards being authentic, because if there truly wouldn't be anything
[SPEAKER_04]: If that disquiet wouldn't be there, then it would not be necessary to seek sensual pleasures or to find that, let's say, full sense of safety, because all that would be unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can ask yourself, like, so, if I don't do anything, will I suffer?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, in the sense of, like, I just suspend all my engagements that I might have accumulated over time, and I just don't commit to anything, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Will I
[SPEAKER_02]: Will that uncertainty start to show up?
[SPEAKER_02]: If it does, it's not because, like...
[SPEAKER_02]: The uncertainty is a result of you not having the engagements anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's that these things were covering up the uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_02]: But often, it's seen the other way around.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if I start to practice restraint or renunciation, I am suffering because I'm restraining myself now.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's that unpleasantness that comes when you don't give in.
[SPEAKER_02]: That is what was already there, kind of lurking, and you were sweeping it under the rug.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: By distracting yourself with pleasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's not so much a movement towards something positive, say, that one doesn't have right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a sort of... it's inverted.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like an uncovering of something which is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop doing certain things, most importantly, like through virtue and sensuousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop doing certain things,
[SPEAKER_02]: So that what's already there can become clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, rather than seeing it more as...
[SPEAKER_02]: I've heard that similarly used before.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have a glass with water in it, and it has mud in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you need to stop shaking it, so that the mud will go to the bottom.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that would usually be used in the context of focusing the mind and concentration techniques.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in this case, it is exactly what you're doing, but in terms of your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop stirring it up through greed, aversion, and delusion, so that it all sinks to the bottom, and you can start
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognizing that dirt where it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, and it's... that's where you will start to see what that... those underlying tendencies, where the mind kind of... in and of itself, it just needs or has certain pressures, certain inclinations that it has to give in to,
[SPEAKER_02]: And, eh... you would only start recognizing that if you stop feeding them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's... that is why authenticity is important to understanding the dhamma, because the things that need to be abandoned and addressed and overcome are things that
[SPEAKER_00]: are very easy to ignore, are things that are very easy to overlook.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the default tendency is not to see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what Greed, Aversion, and Delusion are, they're not these objects or
[SPEAKER_04]: And there are entities in front of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're not like direct perceptions that you can get.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is all on that same level of the things that you're covering up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why lack of authenticity would essentially make you incapable of recognizing your own defilements.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because everything you do is already based on them, like way down the line.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you possibly see the source of the river, to put it that way?
[SPEAKER_00]: The source of the pollution, you're already engaged with the dirt that comes way, way past it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that's why it's not like a philosophical concept only.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has very acute significance to
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognizing what craving is, because you can't abandon craving if you haven't recognized it to begin with.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so people need to recognize that to actually come to terms with craving is going to be unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But can we make it more explicit why that is so?
[SPEAKER_04]: For example, like what is the most dear or cherished thing that is most difficult to give up?
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, what is going to be challenged, let's say inwardly, for lack of a better word, if if one is come to terms with craving?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or what is it that is fueled and maintained by craving?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, what I'm trying to get at is that it is one's own identity that at some point is going to be challenged by all this.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, perhaps you could say that
[SPEAKER_04]: Safety and security, yeah, it begins by outer comfort and distraction and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, fundamentally, one sort of takes refuge in oneself, as you sort of said already somewhat earlier.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, that needs to go as well, if one wants to gain the true refuge in terms of dhamma.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, one's own identity comes up for, let's say, in investigation as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you remove, like, the
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no outer ways that you were covering up that recognition.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's basically impossible that you'll get to that core, which is your identity, if you still maintain the things that are a result of that identity, let's say.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the sensual, perverse, distracted actions, the looted, careless actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no way that you will see
[SPEAKER_00]: The source of where that's coming from, which is the identity, if you're still maintaining it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why authenticity is not just a choice of, like, taking up a certain attitude as you would just, like, change your mindset or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is bound with the choices that you make.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, there are certain choices that you can't make and be fully authentic at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those are the things that go against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the things that an arahant cannot do, most fundamentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: The five things that an arahant cannot do is like killing, stealing, lying, sexual intercourse, and taking intoxicants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any of those things, by doing them, you are being inauthentic.
[SPEAKER_00]: To a varying degree, of course, but fundamentally, if you're training yourself, those things need to go for you to uncover, start uncovering the stuff that you cover up by doing them.
[SPEAKER_04]: And now, if someone has been following this so far, and a sense of anxiety begins to arise, then what?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you want to also question that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't assume that just because you're feeling anxiety, it's necessarily correct.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is the basis for me experiencing this anxiety?
[SPEAKER_02]: It has to be based on
[SPEAKER_02]: Recognition of things that you're genuinely liable to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't fabricate that sense of anxiety to kind of give yourself a boost of sense of urgency in the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be something that is already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not, like, creating it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you recognize the things that already are lurking there in your experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Your own body, you don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no access to the gears and the mechanism that keep it working.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's how your basic organs function.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, you realize, on that level, that anxiety is
[SPEAKER_02]: The anxiety is in things being a certain way.
[SPEAKER_02]: The anxiety is not something you fabricate.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, the practice then is, once a person starts to feel that anxiety in that right way,
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, the practice is not to, like, fix the anxiety or resolve it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's to go through it, so to say, so that that anxiety ceases to cause you suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, as the Buddha said, like, impermanence, uncertainty, suffering and not-self, these are the characteristics of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like... or your entire experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like...
[SPEAKER_02]: Things are that way only when you're ignorant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the fact of the aggregates being suffering, being unsatisfactory, will remain always.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when you're not ignorant anymore, these things are still anxious, but you are not subject to anxiety anymore, because you're not invested in them anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's how... that's that kind of perpendicular direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Instead of, like, doing something to the anxiety or covering it up or managing it, you find a way so that it's... it just doesn't... it just doesn't affect you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I came up with an analogy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like you have a bucket or a barrel that's going to be filled with liquid.
[SPEAKER_02]: The solution to freedom from suffering is not to limit the amount of liquid that's going to come in, or the types of liquid that are going to come in.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's to make it so that the barrel has no bottom.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that, basically, there is no type of anxiety that would be capable of overwhelming your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like
[SPEAKER_00]: The anxiety is limited now, and that's why I don't get overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's... you want to go in the direction of making yourself immovable to any amount of anxiety, let alone... like, you have to overcome not just physical pain and things that can come from other people.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your own mind, fundamentally, that has these susceptibility to these emotions, the states, and that's what you have to overcome.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, this anxiety is related to a sense of groundlessness, to the point that one has not understood that there will be anxiety.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, rather, one will be affected by anxiety, which is suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, anxiety that's not resisted, or anxiety that's properly understood, is not suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, it might feel pessimistic,
[SPEAKER_02]: When you have wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you understand, then it's just the way things are.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just realist.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you can have the right type of joy and the right type of peace.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the face of anxiety, not at the expense of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And here you should perhaps also emphasize that, you know, for some people this anxiety might border on, let's say, depression.
[SPEAKER_04]: And depression can be, in general terms, characterized as the mind begins to sink and you don't know
[SPEAKER_04]: How to climb out of that, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the virtue and the sense restraints, in this case, provide sort of a scaffolding for you to hold on to, that it doesn't become too much.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, on the one hand, we could say that perhaps this anxiety is never going to fully reveal itself without having the virtue and the sense which takes place beforehand.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, on one level, there is sort of a buffer.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if one doesn't restrain oneself, this is never going to happen.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, one can get sort of caught in this intermediate space.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, the the way to not be overwhelmed is, in fact, to attend more closely to
[SPEAKER_04]: One's virtue and one's sense restraints, if one doesn't want to practically become overwhelmed by the anxiety that's going to arise, if one moves into the, let's say, genuine authenticity here.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can we say that, like, virtue and sense restraint kind of make one face this anxiety, but, like, progressively, with, like, the right type of basis, instead of, like, just being confronted, like, to the full extent of it, like, at the moment of death, or when one
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because the minds... because if it's done rightly, it will be a training on their minds.
[SPEAKER_04]: And to the extent that the mind is trained, it will be capable of enduring, basically, things that you now take for granted, falling apart.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's... basically, if a person who hasn't developed virtue is a person who, by default, cannot put up with that uncertainty that would be associated with death, for example, like, they need to try to outrun it in some case, and when they're still healthy,
[SPEAKER_02]: That attempt to outrun the anxiety, the natural uncertainty of the aggregates, manifests through these actions of sensuality and all that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, when death comes, and you can't even move anymore, then all of that stuff that you would be kind of letting out into the world, you can't anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's all kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: contained and the pressure and it starts boiling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's where... that's why it's important, because then, that makes it so that... virtue and sense restraint makes it so that, no matter how much of that internal discomfort and pressure you come up with,
[SPEAKER_02]: It won't go past... your actions, your responses to it, won't go past a certain point.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that, in and of itself, makes it bother you less.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not because, like, you got rid of it, but because you are less invested or less identified with that pressure, just to the extent that you are now able to not do things on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really that need to respond to the anxiety in some way or another that makes you liable to it, because that's the craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: The craving is not like the presence of this.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the fact that you need to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, feel that you need to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And the interesting thing is, there are actually quite a few discourses where somebody, where some monk is like gravely ill, and basically on his deathbed,
[SPEAKER_04]: And then somebody calls the Buddha and says, well, out of compassion, have a talk with this monk.
[SPEAKER_04]: And quite frequently, that monk actually attains one of the stages on account of having a conversation with the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_04]: But why is that so?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because he's already no longer interested in sensual pleasures, because he's about to die.
[SPEAKER_04]: He's just lying there, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: So the usual comforts and the escapes
[SPEAKER_04]: That's all cut off.
[SPEAKER_04]: The whole significance of that has ceased.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, again, it's an understanding that there is rebirth and all the rest of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's still meaningful to attend rightly to what the Buddha is saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, in that situation, it clicks.
[SPEAKER_04]: But this doesn't mean that one should wait until one is lying on one's death bed and feeling miserable.
[SPEAKER_04]: But rather, that's why the context should be understood.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, why did it click for that, let's say, newcomer, who was just a bhikkhu for a few months, and he already became a sotāpanna there, on account of listening to the Buddha, because he found himself in situations where, basically,
[SPEAKER_04]: The usual avenues of distraction and comfort were just no longer there anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he was forced to be authentic, in other words.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he was forced to be authentic, but it would now be very inauthentic to start waiting for that situation to happen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, because, as we were saying before,
[SPEAKER_02]: The virtue...
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, obviously, as you said, that person was a monk.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would have been happening in the sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if a person didn't take that first step of serious dedication to virtue and sensory strength, then
[SPEAKER_00]: By that time, when these things come, the mind is just going to be reacting so strongly to that confinement, to, like, as I was saying before, like, the room, you was... you left that corner in the room accumulating dirt for 50, 60 years, and you think that in one evening, now, you're going to clean it up.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, through virtue and sense restraint, you would... you would force... like, you would make it so that
[SPEAKER_00]: The anxiety would be certainly still unpleasant, but not to the point where it would overwhelm you and make you incapable of contemplating things rightly, because if that has been built up for so long, there's very little chance that you could overcome it, just in a short period of time, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, the attempt to overcome it is going to be super effectively craving, because now it's like, you're really trying to just run away from the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't have that perspective now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, it's now like a knee-jerk, impulsive reaction to how do I solve this as quickly as possible, because now it's in front of me.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, that's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be able to do it in like a balanced, sort of reflexive, detached manner, as you would when you're still healthy, relatively at least.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you shouldn't wait until you're old, or you're sick, or you're near death.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so how is one gonna bring death then, let's say, in the present?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because someone might hold the view that death is a one-time event at the end of life, right?
[SPEAKER_04]: That's probably the most common view.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you see, as long as somebody keeps death at arm's length, basically, like, oh, it's not here, it's going to happen to me later on, 10 years, 20 years, and so on, on account of holding that view, one deprives oneself of understanding what death is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, because you yourself keep pushing it in the future.
[SPEAKER_04]: So,
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if rightly contemplating death is going to be useful in the context of establishing authenticity, then how can people start thinking rightly about death?
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, when the body is still healthy, it seems to me that it is worthwhile discussing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, as we mentioned before, it's authenticity is... like, recognizing your viability to death is one of the most acute ways of becoming authentic, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is death here and now?
[SPEAKER_03]: Would it be like, just recollecting, like, if I am attached to some things, like some people, and just recognizing that I'm gonna lose them anyway, like whatever I'm doing, and just trying to stay with that pressure that one is feeling on account of losing something?
[SPEAKER_03]: Would it be like that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Describing?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or describing about death is?
[SPEAKER_03]: What, like, what one, how one could, like, recollect death correctly?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because death is just like... we just lose everything that we know and everything that we are attached to.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it's like just recollecting this, trying to see if actually I'm attached to something and this attachment makes me suffer.
[SPEAKER_03]: Anyway, I'm gonna lose it, so... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you're saying it's already guaranteed that whatever you're holding on to is going to be taken away from you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just a question of time, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, are you saying that one comes closer to death by making an effort to ask if this would be taken away from me, if that would be taken away from me?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is my mind going to be affected and disturbed by that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes or no?
[SPEAKER_04]: And if you can be without those things, good.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, you know, at some point it will come closer.
[SPEAKER_04]: It might start with external things, my house, my car.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then maybe people
[SPEAKER_04]: Family, children, but in the end, it needs to come closer still.
[SPEAKER_04]: Body, senses, memory, and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is where, well, that is where the real anxiety begins to arise, because that's the very foundation of one's experience.
[SPEAKER_04]: But now you're saying that barrel shouldn't have a bottom.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what are you taking as a foundation of your experience?
[SPEAKER_04]: At some point, it needs to come to that.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's probably not really going to land if one is still fully attached to all these external things.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there is sort of a movement there.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, this shouldn't become an intellectual game.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or something that you occasionally do, this has to become the backdrop.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, am I living my life right now in such a way that I'm not building up any new attachments?
[SPEAKER_04]: And can I come to terms with things that I unfortunately have already become attached to?
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's sort of two tracks and that are there simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then the question is, well, I better not start building up new attachments, because that's moving in the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_04]: And there is still
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's the contradiction right there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You you will be arguing, you essentially, you will have a debate with death and you can't win.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, there's no bargaining with death.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so then, so then, yeah, so that's why virtue and senses change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, again, it's, it's, you won't be able to see how you depend on your body or your feelings and stuff if you still depend on external things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the, the, the
[SPEAKER_02]: In fact, the body, when people are projected into these externals, that's exactly why they end up conceiving the body as another kind of external thing, like just the outside shell of, you know, sensations or things that I can directly perceive, not realizing that the body is actually much more fundamental than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would actually have to withdraw yourself from these things to recognize
[SPEAKER_00]: What that more fundamental dependence is, which would ultimately make death be uncomfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're not holding on to any of these things, again, not as a matter of choice, but as a matter of
[SPEAKER_00]: Having understood that anxiety, and having understood how it's there on its own, you didn't create it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you, basically, having gratuitous assumptions of moving away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, if you have that understanding, then you would be unmoved by that anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it all starts with that, because
[SPEAKER_00]: Virtue and social chain on the right level, taken on the right level, it's not just the adherence to external behavior, as we've said before.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be done with that recognition of, like, through these actions, through this absence from these actions, I am wearing away my dependence on things that are not in my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to keep that connection
[SPEAKER_00]: As the context to your virtue, not like I just do these practices and behaviors.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you would start to see as well, the wrong motivations for keeping the virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: If those things start to come up, well, those would be other dependencies as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: As we discussed before in the talk about virtue and observances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that would be another way of
[SPEAKER_00]: Being inauthentic, like doing the the observances, because even not necessarily for the adherence to an external tradition, but just automatically, just doing it without that context of, you know, your liability to suffering and how this is
[SPEAKER_00]: Related to that, would make it automatically just be just habits that you're just following for no particular reason.
[SPEAKER_04]: So... Yeah, that is the sīla-vatthaparamāsa.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that is the wrong grasp of habits and virtues and duties.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that might come with, let's say, some rewards or externally there might things even
[SPEAKER_04]: They might make things externally more comfortable even, and one can just fall asleep in a little corner in your kuti somewhere, entirely missing the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so the virtue would only prepare you for death, if it's taken on that right level, with the recognition of how, through this, these things that would make death
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the less death can take away from you, basically, the less you suffer when death comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, as you said before, that's another thing to point out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very...
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a very good test to see, like, what are you... what really is the extent of your commitment to the practice, to ask yourself... yeah, sure, we all start with attachments that we already have, but is your practice... like, are you still actively accumulating new attachments, in spite of you saying that you're trying to...
[SPEAKER_02]: To be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, somebody who is... who is... says they're practicing the dhamma to be free from suffering, but at the same time is allowing themselves to build up new attachment that they didn't have before, that's already like... that has to be done because they're covering up, again, the inauthenticity.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're covering up
[SPEAKER_02]: How these things are basically perpetuating and proliferating the same problem that they're trying to be free from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and it's often... that's the thing with inauthenticity.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a... it's a form of ignorance, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's... with all types of ignorance,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there because you're not aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not that people choose to be inauthentic in the same way that people don't choose to be ignorant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, it has to be done with a certain degree of... Negligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, with not... Well, that's what negligence and heedfulness is, essentially.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like recognizing
[SPEAKER_00]: The things that you're already liable to, and how your actions are making it worse, are making it better.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, also, as we said before, like, if someone feels the need to, let's say, defend their views, or defend their practices, when questioned or challenged, or they fall in love with their teacher, or they cannot leave their monastery, because that's the only place where I can practice, all of these are
[SPEAKER_04]: Indications that you are basically building up new attachments and that you're having the whole thing backwards.
[SPEAKER_04]: That should be a red flag there.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it seems to me that, like, for a complete newcomer to just spend some time alone and inwardly not see yourself as part of a group, and then take on some virtue and sense-retraint, that is how I think practically all of this starts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right?
[SPEAKER_04]: And also...
[SPEAKER_04]: Even thinking about death, even if it is not that intense, it doesn't go that far, that will already pull you out of the crowd, for the simple reason that no one else can die for you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right?
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to face your death alone.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, however much you want to lose yourself in an anonymous day,
[SPEAKER_04]: Thinking about death rightly will bring the whole thing back to you, which is unpleasant, but it can't be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the person should also realize when that... like, if there is anything in the world that could bother you, or could take away your peace,
[SPEAKER_02]: That is what the dhamma is supposed to address.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's something that can be easily overlooked by just not thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, people would fall into the idea that the dhamma is about getting special experiences and special, like, mystical insights and stuff.
[SPEAKER_02]: But how many people actually ask themselves
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, but in spite of all this, are there still things that, if they happen to me, or if they're taken away from me, I could still suffer?
[SPEAKER_02]: If yes, then, regardless of all this other stuff, I can't tell myself, if I'm being authentic, that this is what the dhamma is about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like it's wrong on some kind of specific doctrinal grounds to be getting these experiences, because it doesn't fit with the sutta, such and such.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because if
[SPEAKER_02]: If you know that this is not addressing your liability to anything, it can be like the most...
[SPEAKER_02]: Kind of distant, unrealistic scenario.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if there is anything that you feel could undermine you, if it happens, that is what the dhamma should be about.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, when a person starts to feel that, yeah, that anxiety, or uncover, really, that anxiety that we mentioned, whether it's very strong or not, you have to ask yourself
[SPEAKER_02]: This is... tell yourself this is what the practice is about.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I might not be able to take it on fully, like you might kind of look at that corner, that dirty corner, and it might feel overwhelming.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not like you have to take it all at once, but you certainly shouldn't lose the recognition that I am not free, I am not practicing, or I have not
[SPEAKER_02]: I successfully practiced the Buddhist teaching, until that thing cannot be there, even if I want to.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not because I stopped acknowledging that anxiety, but like, I fully commit myself to try to bring it up, and it just can't happen.
[SPEAKER_02]: But most people, it's just like, because you're not aware of it, you naturally just don't look in that direction, and you can spend your whole life building certain
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, coping mechanisms and strategies, again, without even noticing, that allow you not to think about that, because it's just too... And ironically, a lot of what is nowadays being taught as meditation, helps with not looking at that dark corner.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just focus over here, so that you don't need to be there, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the thing is, as well, one of the red flags, as related to what we just mentioned, is that it immediately just gives you pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like, right from the start, there was no accumulation of dirt from all this infinite, endless saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was just, you got the pleasure right away.
[SPEAKER_02]: You didn't have to toil through the cleaning of the crap that was there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just, very quickly, you got the pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's a red flag, because if, like, these
[SPEAKER_02]: You've been going with the grain so hard, and so long, that going in the opposite direction cannot be easy.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not that it's impossible, but you should be skeptical of anything that just feels easy.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's where the effort is, you see.
[SPEAKER_02]: The effort is not in trying to
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not about gain, like committing yourself to a meditation technique, doing it so hard, 24-7.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's about uncovering these things, uncovering them, and then getting to the point where you can face them without fear, essentially.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not building something, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like you are taking stuff away,
[SPEAKER_00]: Until there's nothing left.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no cover-ups left.
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't... that kind of assumption, often people, when they sign up for such retreat and method, the assumption is that I can regain some control, you know, because my world appears to be
[SPEAKER_02]: And ironically, you would be more closely seeing or becoming authentic by saying, wait, no, I am liable for things to go out of my control.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then that's that's the solution nobody wants to hear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if you have, if you have, like, I don't know, you have a leak in your house,
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's like, I don't know, you see these these little marks of water on the roof.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to hear that you have to replace the whole plumbing system.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to be told that you have to remove the entire foundation of the house.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will like contractor who says, oh yeah, just painting is needed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it will be fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, it's your own loss because, like, it is, like, you might live your whole life.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's basically a degree where these things can generally seem to stay with you
[SPEAKER_02]: Until the day you die, like work, the management methods, cover-up methods.
[SPEAKER_02]: But at the very least, at that moment, it's gonna have to stop working.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's where your aggregates simply won't listen to you anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of that stuff that you were covering up, it will force itself to the surface.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can't... At that moment, you can't just focus on sensations.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your senses might be breaking apart, so what sensation are you going to focus on?
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, you see, then the thing is, if one brings death from, let's say, the future to the present, what one will have to recognize is that actually that's already the case right now.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So it's not like, oh, I'll just live my life and then I just hope I have a peaceful death, by which people mean, like, you know, get a shot of morphine or you die in your sleep, hoping to avoid the unpleasant sensation.
[SPEAKER_04]: But with death as such, they're not concerned.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whereas actually, death reflected properly, reveals you how, as you said, things already are.
[SPEAKER_04]: Namely, aggregates are fundamentally already doing their own thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's a... it would be... yeah, it's an unfortunate misconception to think that death is like these, I don't know, intense bodily pain or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that event, those sensations or those those things are going to come at that moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, but really, death is just...
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the final confirmation of the fact that these aggregates are not yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just... so that recognition is... like death is buried into or underlying every... your experience now, because the aggregates are already not in your control.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's... it's... you have a certain... it's like you're a dead man walking, essentially.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can walk, but that doesn't mean that you can ever
[SPEAKER_02]: escape your liability.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can do stuff on top of your liability, but not to actually change it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what, like, anatta means.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't mean that you don't have control in any way, like you're just a robot who is, like, deterministically bound to make certain actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means that whatever action you choose to do, there is that foundation that undermines it always.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't just, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't assume yourself to be the master.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that... like that's bad enough for for it to not be worth taking itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only take it itself if you know that it will go your way.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if there's even a little chance that somebody else is going to come, like, I don't know, you're building you're building a house, but then
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody tells you, yeah, you're building it, but there is a chance that at any point in time, somebody's going to come, and you're going to have to give it over to them, and you're going to have to leave.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not going to... if you keep that recognition in your mind, it will be impossible for you to start treating it internally, like, no, this is my house.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's what anatta is about, and that's why all these things would only be realized, again, through authenticity, because
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all in that direction of lack of control that's experienced as, initially, as unpleasant and unsettling.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, not in itself, but because you have the need, through habitual engagement, to control it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's like a momentum that is kept going.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then,
[SPEAKER_02]: You suddenly put a stop to it and it's like it wants to keep... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...keep going.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why... that's the discrepancy that you feel.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's where... and that's where the endurance begins.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, the moment you hit the brake,
[SPEAKER_02]: You better have a seatbelt or else you'll be flying through the window.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or it's like the the dog, that's something of the wild animals, compared to the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like only when you actually pin them down, finally just stop running with them, that's when you start feeling the pull.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, it can... it's everything, just... there's sensuality, there's the the core stuff, but even if if
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't really experience those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when you're old, for example, you might not have that intense core sensual desire that you had when you were young, but that doesn't mean that you're free.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still have, fundamentally, that need for things to go your way, to some degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if there's anything that can upset you, anything that can... that can disturb your peace, that means you haven't come to terms with
[SPEAKER_00]: That fundamental uncertainty of your own experience.